[SPEAKER_00]: I was wondering if we can speak about life and death, those two phenomenons, and death being the counterpart of life.
[SPEAKER_00]: But first, there's a sutta, and it's called fragile or perishable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I will teach you the fragile and the unfragile, the perishable and the unperishable.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the fragile and what is the unfragile?
[SPEAKER_00]: Form is the fragile.
[SPEAKER_00]: Its cessation, subsiding, passing away, is the unfragile.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, feeling is the fragile, perception is the fragile, intentions are fragile, consciousness is fragile.
[SPEAKER_00]: The cessation, subsiding, passing away, is unfragile, unperishable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That fact of the change remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, those things, those particular things change,
[SPEAKER_00]: In various ways, they're subject to change, but one thing that is not up for debate or subject to change is that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're ending.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in terms of, like, we have the phenomenon of life,
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's counterpart.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, here's life, everything that I'm experiencing now.
[SPEAKER_00]: The all, if I can say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Myself included.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the background to that is this change, is this death.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've got to understand death as... the background of death is implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because it's usually, like, death is perceived to be something at the end of the life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when that time comes, then death will arrive, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, death is already here, through the fact that you were manifested, that you were born.
[SPEAKER_01]: Already implies, as we say often, like, the
[SPEAKER_01]: The manifestation of a thing, anything, any phenomenon, big or small, far or near, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Manifestation of a thing is its impermanence, the fact that it's manifested, the fact that it came to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's incomprehensible to you to stop that or prevent that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just... it's inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: The manifestation of things, the presentation of phenomena, it's... it's just something that's completely outside of your scope.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, death, kind of, it's on... obviously, it's on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just in this... in a general sense, if you take a phenomenon of your life, the all that happens while you're alive, well, the implication of that life is that it is... that it has come to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, its cessation is implicit in its manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said, like, those who are
[SPEAKER_01]: Unmindful, they're as if dead already.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you don't have to wait to die in order to be within death.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do is exist within the Mara's domain, or within the domain of that which implies death, that's already as if dead, because death is there through that implication.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you see...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you see life, you will see its counterpart existing in the background.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's implication.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot arise without that implication of death, life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means it cannot arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you know, the fact that it is manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it cannot be conceived separate from.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot be conceived without that implication.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the broadest sense of that... of that word.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the point is... it's like... well, think of it like... like a simile.
[SPEAKER_01]: Say somebody is living within a waiting trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: The big trap is just waiting to crush you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're completely unaware of the trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're completely unaware of the... the thing hanging over your head.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have absolutely... well, by being completely unaware that it's a trap, you have absolutely no notion of escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if you were to... even if somebody tell you, oh, it's a trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you don't even know where to begin.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you don't even recognize it, you don't even know that there is anything to be escaped or how to be escaped.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's pretty much the existence of anyone who is living within the sensual domain with the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: I being Kutujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they are as if dead already.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, yes, technically,
[SPEAKER_01]: Their life, their birth, is still manifested there, because they're still existing, but within the domain of the inevitable trap, inevitable cessation of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can see there and then, while they're in that state, by not having the right view, by not being a sensory strain, you know, like, they don't even know, they don't even have a notion of the escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as such, they might as well be dead already.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's the other... if you cultivate the context of death, then you cannot delight in life.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll turn away from life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, as it says in the Sutta, upekkhā will be established, or the counterpart will be established, but meaning the context will be clear, death in the background, implicit.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you cultivate that
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, on the basis of the same simile, if you get the right view and you recognize the trap as a trap, you recognize that whatever has the nature of arising, that's why it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever has the nature to manifest, that is its impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize the extent of the trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you then contemplate
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything, in every in-breath, in every out-breath, as the suttas would say...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, in that context, and we said it before, but, you know, it doesn't hurt to repeat it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The contemplation of death in the suttas that's often talked about, when it says, like, a monk should contemplate within an in-breath, within an out-breath, he shouldn't, like, he should contemplate death.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean he's doing it on the level.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just means that his knowledge, his
[SPEAKER_01]: Correct, concurrent, attending to the implicit death of this life, permeates even the most immediate action of breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you contemplate death on the level of in-breath and out-breath, not by watching sensations of in-breath and out-breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: You contemplate it by developing that background context of the implication of that death so thoroughly,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, even breathing will remain... cannot remain unaffected by that context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, any... even the core of life, the sign of life, breath, heartbeat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the most neutral kind of habitual
[SPEAKER_01]: Action that you generally take for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even that will be permeated by the significance of the implication of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you do that not just for the sake of, you know, contemplate death so hard to reach that point where you just kind of... boom!
[SPEAKER_01]: You just step outside of it and you're free.
[SPEAKER_01]: You contemplate it so that there is a complete dispassion towards anything regarding life.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you're free.
[SPEAKER_01]: When there is no more passion towards that step... Well, that removes you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically cancels you within that implication of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, you disappear from the trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you have no issue if a random trap falls if you are not in that trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's not your problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot be your problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's only a problem when you are the one who's going to be trapped or hit by that thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, obviously, ordinarily, people will... everybody knows, I'm going to die.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that thought stands for something abstract in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stands for the idea of death, which is like a very much, as I said,
[SPEAKER_01]: Misconceived notion of something that will happen at the end, whenever that end is, and so on, in the future, with time...
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's so disconnected from this life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you don't wait for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't... Well, you know, if you need to wait for the actual dying to contemplate death, it's too late.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you contemplate it within life, within that which was born, within that birth, within that manifestation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although people know that, well, they already, when they think it's at the end of my life, that it ends in the future, even if you had to cultivate their thought every day, for example, like some Stoics might have done, not that they did exactly this, but maybe at the end of their day, they might think, well, I might die tomorrow, or, you know, death is coming, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And
[SPEAKER_00]: And they might cultivate that particular thought, abstract thought, about death being in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not in the sense that we're talking about, but being somewhere else, at some other point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not connected with... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not connected with...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the heart of their own present existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a person like that, who, if they had to somehow find the effort to do that every day, have those abstract notions of death, still might be a bit more careful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, no, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's better than being completely, like, ignorant or like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Deluded in regard to it, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's better to not forget that you will die, even in that kind of abstract, secondary, remote sense, that usual kind of idea of death is for people.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's better than nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But,
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when the Buddha was describing the contemplation of death, that leads to, like, the quickest way of dispassion and arahantship, it has to be taken very, very differently, much more acutely, much more precisely, and much more profusely.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were thinking about death as an abstract thing in the future, coming, and your mind becomes
[SPEAKER_00]: More grateful for the present things of life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind goes into the direction of delighting in life, really appreciating all the moments and all the things that can happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think that is a sign that you are not connecting this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's very nice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, again, take the simile of the trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, if you're contemplating
[SPEAKER_01]: Pretty much any contemplation... Life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Life, if it's done acutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Death, if it's done acutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: Contemplation of a trap, acutely, you recognize that, oh, it's not something that will come later.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's right there now, as I think it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's hanging over my head.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you then spend time going around saying thank you to other people within the same trap and expressing your gratitude?
[SPEAKER_01]: You might say it in passing, if it comes up, while you are being preoccupied.
[SPEAKER_01]: with how to free myself from the impending thing that's going to crash on my head in this trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm so grateful for this bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, like, so it's even when people contemplate it, in that sense you described those people, not everybody, but then that death is still kind of removed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, yes, it's a trap and everything, but the fact that you think you have time
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you go out and appreciate things, you wouldn't appreciate stuff if you're aware of the imminent danger of that stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, only when that imminence is removed, you can kind of, okay, let me deal with this, and then I'll deal with it when it comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's like recognizing the imminence, the implicit aspects.
[SPEAKER_00]: The life is the trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: The life is the death.
[SPEAKER_00]: The death, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot have it otherwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's like the separation, because people see it separately.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, the separation, because of the the accumulated wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they don't see it simultaneously, as the counterpart to life is, is surrounded.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, it's, it's shell.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they don't see it simultaneously, because seeing things simultaneously requires training against the grain, against the directionality of your senses, of your mind, of everything you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't do it accidentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't accidentally stumble upon the clear image and the relationship between life and death that would result in the immediate dispassion you become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can, through repetition and through kind of digging up that way, against the grain of your senses, against the grain of life, against that flow of, you know, forward movement, so to speak, that generally is how people's lives go.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it takes that effort to swim against the current.
[SPEAKER_01]: And one of the obvious ways of doing that is taking on the precepts, celibacy, sense restraint, and then the contemplation of that, like, death, however remote, delayed, non-imminent might have been, it's gonna start narrowing down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you are not maintaining the cover-up of the imminence of death,
[SPEAKER_01]: Through your actions of sensuality, you will be non-restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're containing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you're going to start discerning it on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, those who are mindful of death... Well, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, not being forgetful of that context is the beginning of that right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those who are forgetful, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: those who are unmindful, they're as if dead already.
[SPEAKER_01]: And only those who are mindful have an opportunity, have the... To, yeah, eventually penetrate it on that acute level and understand and see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would then result, not as I said, in some magical mystical experience, but in complete dispassion towards anything concerned with life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't mean they delight in death either.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just mean they contemplated sufficiently enough to cancel out delight in life.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's enough for liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, someone gets that context of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do they remember it?
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you keep it going throughout the day?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, you're going to be forgetting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be getting distracted.
[SPEAKER_01]: You keep yourself from drifting away too far from it by policing and restraining your own actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which are delighting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which would be, exactly, which would be countering that context of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, if you're acting out of sensuality, you have to put life first.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to put the pleasure of life even more first.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's already a serious perversion of that actual order.
[SPEAKER_01]: And whenever you pervert the order, you cover up what's implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the right... in that order.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by delighting in life, by perpetuating, proliferating delight through acts of sensuality, acting out of ill-will, acting out of hindrances regarding life and things that come up within that life, you are covering up the implication of death in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And every time you cover it up, the view that death is something later, gets established more and more.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you...
[SPEAKER_00]: I suppose you also have to feel, like, threat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's an immediate threat.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not... You certainly would, initially.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's very important, if you want to go down the... down this route of contemplating death, in similar contexts, you better have your aggregator virtue properly established.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because otherwise the mind is just going to start freaking out in regard to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it will realize that there is no shelter up, down, above, below, behind, forward.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything, in any direction, I go to seek shelter for myself, it's under death.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's under the rule of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in death, it is implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it's not safe.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, only person, they will not be overwhelmed by that, is the person who already contained the mind from spilling over too far and in these irrational attempts of seeking, seeking safety, that would then result in its own derangement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because then, in a way...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if your aggregate of virtue is developed, then it's... even though death is that threat to life...
[SPEAKER_01]: It can feel as a threat in everybody, but it will be contained, because you have contained that which is under the threat of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, although you still have
[SPEAKER_01]: Some horses in that race, so to speak, in other words, you're not completely, fully dispassionate towards life, you have con... you have contained all those unwholesome ways of making your dependence on that trap even worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you start recognizing the trap and that which would be destroyed by the trap, you might feel some intensity, but overall it's contained because your actions have been purified beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you can take it further.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a person would feel the threat and freak out, only if they haven't contained that... Yeah, they might, like, again, whatever that intensity, at the time, might feel like the highest intensity, because it's not like you can be outside of that experience and compare it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, like, whatever is the current pain, it's the worst pain in everyone's life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever is the current worry, it's the worst worry.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, whether they're doing it rightly or not, they can see how close to breaking the precept and acting out they are, or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, in hindsight, when they look back, a week ago, when I started contemplating death and so on, yes, it felt close, it felt acute, it felt scary, but I haven't done anything on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that will already bring confidence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the measure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Have you done anything on account of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: And how bad was it?
[SPEAKER_01]: How bad did your mind make you act?
[SPEAKER_00]: Good, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the face of that felt intent, that threat, because like, well, I can think about death, I'm not afraid of death, like many people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I think about death, I'm not afraid of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the death they're thinking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gurudev, when you feel a threat of pain, a little bit, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly, there, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like if a person wants to contemplate, start contemplating death, if they say, feel like their virtue is decent, they've been restraining, guarding the sense doors, they're not breaking the precepts, they're not engaging with sensuality, they're celibate and so on, and they want to practice, you know, a bit of a
[SPEAKER_01]: A sharper approach, such as death contemplation, you don't start by your ideas of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just pick up something that's dear to you and imagine it being taken away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where that feeling of pain is, that's where death is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, take it and further there and practice dispassion towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's also, yes, finding that those signs of death, almost, you know, picking up that flavor of death, you know, seeing, imagining...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, those flavors are actually to be found in things that you don't... that somebody might not necessarily associate with death, with their idea of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're finally not getting what you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being paired with what you don't want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being separated from what you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: All these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are examples of dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wherever there is dukkha, the direction of dukkha, that's where death is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, contemplate things that would cause you suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you are contemplating death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you take it further and it's like, yeah, so I would be afraid.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would be...
[SPEAKER_01]: I would be affected.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would suffer if I lose the loved ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, imagine how much more then.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through that same dukkha of contemplating losing the loved ones, imagine losing also these senses on account of which you have your loved ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's gonna feel even worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so have... imagine those things, contemplate that, but then pick up this... that... the sign of death, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, feel it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, as I said, only on the basis of thoroughly developed virtue, because otherwise...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, this is not something that the Buddha was teaching to householders.
[SPEAKER_01]: By householders, meaning people that are not celibate.
[SPEAKER_01]: People that might occasionally take on virtue and, you know, go to monastery and keep their priesthood for a week or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because for most people who love life, love things in life, their families, their children, whatever, getting the flavor of death,
[SPEAKER_00]: It means turning away from it and forgetting about it, never thinking about it again, and just indulging more into life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Love life even harder, because just cover it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you had to give such a person the threat of death, while they were still delighting so much in that life... Well, you get what the suttas describe.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they heard the Buddha describe nibbāna,
[SPEAKER_01]: From their standpoint of very much cherishing life, possessions, and everything else, they would have, as the suttas describe, they fell on the ground, beating their breasts, pulling their hair, and saying like, oh, that will kill us, that will destroy us.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like people in, on death row, in some of these, in America, they don't, they're on death row, but they, they could be executed any day.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's always this threat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hanging over their head, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they are not really wanting to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would rather not distract themselves from that, which they go crazy, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like the worst kind of torture.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, that's what Dostoevsky was writing about in The House of Dead.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the prison, from his experience in the prison, basically, he saw that the worst punishment to give to a man that, you know, a man, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: a householder that loves life, that does not see the problem in sensuality, is to, like, have a perpetual possibility of execution.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there were people there, they were insane, in their death row, and they might be killed tomorrow, they might not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes they were taken out to the gallows, and then sent back.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like unbearable, mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they all just disintegrated.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he was, he was affected by, by witnessing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as that other sutta describes, it's like, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: When the man was talking to the Buddha, you brought it up recently, when he said, oh, you know, like, we love life, family, centrality, household life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just the idea of renunciation feels like a precipice, feels like falling into the abyss.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just the idea of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, if renunciation scares you that much, well, imagine how much forceful renunciation will scare you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: When things are forcefully taken away from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you are... basically, where your own mind does the renunciation for you, like, without you wanting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When your senses just fail.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, you already get the flavor through practicing renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's just generally so scary.
[SPEAKER_01]: You say to people, you gotta be celibate.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, like, you put on the greatest fear on them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, forever?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I will never experience the pleasure of the senses again?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, it's like death.
[SPEAKER_01]: From the point of view of those whose minds are still very much imbued with sensuality and do not see danger in that trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: But seeing it as danger, no longer delighting in life, which... Yeah, so, like, you brought up the example of a person who, say, might experience that flavor and then double down in commitment to the life and loving life and family and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if somebody experiences the flavor of death, gets a hint of it, and they might... they recognize they're not able to, like, dwell on it and contemplate it rightly,
[SPEAKER_01]: At least, don't cover it up twice as much as before.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, allow that kind of background hint of that doubt, that fear, to stay there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, you don't have to go fully towards it, if you have not prepared the basis of virtue, sense of strength, liberty and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, at least, don't cover it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't completely cover up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they were.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were puthujjana.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were philosophers.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were religious people.
[SPEAKER_00]: They weren't so intoxicated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they were not withdrawn from sensuality and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they did have the capacity, through practice, to not completely cover that up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it did shape their life more wholesomely.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not ideal, because they still stay puthujjanas.
[SPEAKER_01]: What I'm saying is, if somebody who also has access to the instruction of the dhamma, and then practices that non-complete cover-up of death, well, it would certainly bring you even closer to the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, eventually, you realize, you might realize, that giving up sensuality is not as scary as you thought it was.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you work up towards it, and then... and actually start containing your mind on that level where it matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you do see it right, death rightly, and you start renouncing sensuality, start renouncing the world... Well, no, you gotta start...
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, you might have that, you know, in the beginning...
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, don't cover it up and then start renouncing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That can be like a wake-up call.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm going to die.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's no way I can escape that, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you escape the implication of manifestation?
[SPEAKER_01]: When you yourself, anything you know about yourself, any possession, any ownership, is just another manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a person who's actually moved by that thought and starts doing things rightly, in accordance with it, starts to, like, let me stop being a bit careful, let me find an answer to this issue, and then starts to contemplate it more and more.
[SPEAKER_00]: And finds himself, you know, virtuous, dispassionate towards life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, as that sutta says, you know, either he is fully dispassionate towards life, or upādāna gets established.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like he's in this paranoid fear.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or disgust and hates everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: He might have episodes of that, but again, with the right instruction, which is abundant with the suttas and so on, you recognize, okay, no, it's about
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole dwelling on death, and recollecting it, and not forgetting it, is just so to experience, to develop the complete dispassion towards anything concerned with life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just to that extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not more, not less.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when that dispassion is established, you recognize, okay, so now I neither delight in that life, nor do I delight in death.
[SPEAKER_01]: I certainly don't fear it, because I have nothing to lose anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever's here, will have to not be here, because it's here, for no other reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perceiving life, seeing it correctly, you will see, well, you're basically contemplating in each of their life, counterpart, death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just... and the realization, it's not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is never was mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through this passion, because passion maintains the ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Acting out of passion maintains the ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Possession, consumption, all these ideas, all these notions, all these phenomena, it's just how you maintain the ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: The ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you realize that, when you start contemplating and establish the context that's incompatible,
[SPEAKER_01]: With the growth of passion towards things, the mind just can't go in that direction because of the whole framework of death that's being seen in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you go and reach this fruit to eat it, easily, you enjoy it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, then you suddenly recognize, through discernment, that there is a massive axe waiting to chop your hand each time you reach for the fruit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh!
[SPEAKER_01]: The significance, the joy of the fruit very much changes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It becomes actually dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the taste hasn't changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It all remained the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: It still tastes the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: The greatest fruit ever known to man.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now you see an axe waiting to fall.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, oh, it's not the same thing anymore, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the mind will not go and just, oh, yeah, yeah, give me that fruit, let me reach for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it sees what's implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you contemplate it long enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will stop being scary, because you recognize, well, there's nothing scary about an axe hanging over a random fruit.
[SPEAKER_01]: It becomes scary when my hand is in between the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or my head.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, when you recognize the danger, you don't have to... Well, you have to practice sense restraint because of the habits.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, when that's been thoroughly done, you don't have to then
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop yourself from reaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just by having that context, means mind will not be reaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said, whatever you frequently think and ponder, that's what will become the inclination of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're frequently pondering about the taste of the fruit, and how great it is, and the texture.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the mind isn't losing its broader context, and it's becoming more obsessed and focused on the aspect of the taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: The beauty.
[SPEAKER_01]: The beauty, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you frequently contemplate the hanging axe,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, then the mind is inclining towards avoiding that danger, because it's factually dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, restraint becomes effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to restrain yourself, because you don't want to do it in the first place.